Months ago, I put a million dollars in
this vault, and then on a Super Bowl
commercial, close it up, boys, I said
whoever solved 100 puzzles first spread
all across the internet would win the
money inside. And out of millions of
people, one human cracked the code. And
I'm going to show you guys exactly how
he did it. Boys, pour to me.
>> Yeah.
>> Now, throw me my super expensive
>> YEAH.
>> LAPTOP. TO HAVE WON A million dollars,
you first had to watch my Super Bowl
teaser titled Watch My Super Bowl ad to
win a million dollars. If you went in
the description and clicked on this
playlist, then looked at the pinned
comments of all of these videos, you
would get nine puzzles. And if you
completed them, you'd receive your first
answer, which was every challenge leads
towards location name somewhere around
world.
Great. After hours, I just taught you
how to play the game, and this
is the actual puzzle. And to win the
million dollars, you needed to find 91
locations hidden throughout all these
clues.
So, let's get into it, starting with my
Super Bowl commercial.
I just put $1 million inside this vault.
If you were to group and add these
bright colored bills in the vault
together, and then match those numbers
to letters in the alphabet, you get
cashed in, which sounds like Tashkent,
Uzbekistan, [music] which would be your
first of 12 locations. But do you
remember when I said, "THEN GO WIN $1
MILLION?"
I WAS WEARING A BELT WITH VERY special
X's.
>> Why were they special?
>> These X's were actually wired color code
pairs, and because there's 25 of them,
you could map them to the alphabet,
giving you
Lima, Peru, your second location. The
third was the golden vault door. If you
match these numbers and dots to the
International Scrabble Lexicon, the
message would spell out he funded a
hospital in this site of last year's
Scrabble Championship, which was in
Accra, Ghana.
>> [music]
>> For the fourth puzzle, this bulb is
flashing in Morse code spelling
absolutely nothing. But if you play the
video in reverse, the Morse code pattern
spells Kabul. And if you take the white
tape on the back of my clipboard and
overlay it on the front, you'd spell out
capital of East Nusa Tenggara, which is
Kupang, Indonesia. There are 26 ports
[music] in this store and 10 lasers fire
in a sequence and hit those ports
landing in this order. If you convert
these numbers to the alphabet, it spells
laser mixup. And if you mix up the word
laser, it spells Arles as in Arles,
France.
For the seventh puzzle, each screen's
background color can be read as base
three code. If you use the base three
formula and then convert that to
letters, you get B City Hub built in
Toronto, Canada. And if you convert
these emojis on my phone to text, the
first two letters of each spell the city
name of Casablanca, which is in Morocco.
And did you catch the smoke bomb? This
may look like one plus one, but this is
an S. This is actually a T and this is a
one. And the entire thing is yellow,
which spells out Yellowstone, Wyoming.
And did you see these doors? They have
some pretty weird dots on them. But if
you overlaid these dots together and
counted the numbers from top to bottom,
you'd get these atomic numbers. And if
you turn them into element symbols,
you'd get Lahore, Pakistan.
But my favorite puzzle was probably this
tank. There is a letter I and a painted
picture of a person [music] screaming.
If you sound that out, it sounds like
ice cream. And in 2021, I did a video
where I ate a $100,000 golden ice cream.
And at the 8:20 mark, there is an image
of a receipt, which shows $36,348.26,
[music]
which matches the tank. This receipt was
for a $30,000 bananas [music] foster.
So, why does that matter? Well, bananas
foster was invented in 1951 at the
Brennan's restaurant in New Orleans,
Louisiana. And for the 12th puzzle, if
you take the closed captioning in the
Super Bowl ad, the letters by the dashes
spell seven-letter Big Lodge, which is a
tall inn, aka Tallinn, Estonia. Huh?
Pretty good?
Congratulations, throw yourself a party.
You just solved everything in the Super
Bowl commercial. What if I told you
that's only 10% of the entire puzzle?
We're just getting started. Because in
my pre-game video, this note on the
computer was a puzzle. This calendar was
a puzzle. This Rubik's Cube, obviously,
was a puzzle. These street markings were
a puzzle. Even this million-dollar check
was a puzzle. This license plate was a
puzzle. And all of this was a puzzle as
well.
There was a lot of puzzles. And if
you're wondering how some of them
worked, this is a red Rubik's Cube. And
if you looked at the commercial, this
clue tells us a cube should become a
square. So, a red cube becomes a red
square. That's a place in Moscow,
Russia. And for the crosswalk,
there is no crosswalk in the world that
should look like that.
>> What about the one that you just showed?
>> No, and you can just leave. This monitor
shows a series of pictures, and the
first two letters of these words are
compass directions: north, east, south,
and west. And I don't know if you guys
knew this, but there's actually an
alphabet called flag semaphore. So, to
get the location from this crosswalk,
one arm is already drawn, and the other
arm came from the first two letters from
[music] those pictures on the monitor.
I'll be honest, I have no idea where
this was coming from at this point. But,
if you want to know how to solve the
rest of the puzzles [music] in this
pre-game video, here's the instructions.
Yeah, it's a lot. And since I'm teaching
about puzzles, might as well teach you
how to subscribe. There's a button right
below the video that if you click, it
would mean the world to me if you did.
And by the way, at the end of this
video, I'll tell you how you can solve
the puzzle in this video and win
$10,000.
But, that's at the end. Phase three was
known as the gift puzzles, where I
dropped off this box with a few of my
friends.
>> Thank you. you.
>> HE SENT ME A GIFT from some Super Bowl
commercial.
>> I got a present.
>> Are you sure it's not a million dollars?
>> Each gift had its own unique solution.
For instance, Jimmy Fallon got this. If
you rearrange the letters in the correct
order, this puzzle spells Jimmy's
birthplace.
>> Which Jimmy?
My birthplace. In Wichita, Kansas.
>> Another clue was hidden in a gift I gave
to the Botez sisters. It was a custom
chess set with the message that I did
not intend to be this creepy.
>> Enjoy this new chess set. Maybe you two
can play a game that lasts as long as
game six between Magnus Carlsen and Jan
Nepomniachtchi.
>> Good chess reference. Go Mr. Beast on
his chess knowledge.
>> Thanks, Andrea. But that mention wasn't
random. If you could create the final
position
>> I think we need to find what position it
is, set it up, and try to read the
message.
>> Oh, you're actually on the right track.
But the real question is what could you
>> B U F F A F F U O
>> Buffalo is in New York.
>> That actually makes a lot of sense.
>> I swear I did not help them. Now, they
may have solved that puzzle for you, but
it wasn't exactly smooth sailing for all
my other friends.
>> The angry lot layer.
>> It's kind of cool. Let me try to do the
clue before everyone else does it.
>> Maybe it's a parking lot. 50 49 58.
That's the That's the thing.
>> Well, Sketch, at least you tried.
Quackity then got this sword with
symbols on it, which when deciphered you
get Tierra del Fuego. Airrack's gift
decoded to Algiers, Algeria. Haley
Bailey's rings got you DeKalb, Illinois.
And the totally real diamond that Chris
Hemsworth stole got you Queensland,
Australia.
After those, if you went to our website,
you'd see the final and biggest gift in
this photo. And hopefully you noticed
these panels with weird symbols, which
are actually numbers using a special
code called Torוק. If you convert these
symbols, you get numbers which spells
out a nice sugar. The word nice is
referring to a place in France called
Nice. And the French word for sugar is
sucre, which brings you to Sucre, a
place in Bolivia.
Group four is where things got big.
How big?
Salesforce Tower big.
Group four was all about outreach. By
counting how many seconds each color
stayed on on top of the tower and
mapping those numbers to the letters of
the alphabet, it spelled out a clue
leading to Silver Coast, Portugal. We
even had questions hidden [music] in
billboards.
After solving those, you'd find even
more puzzles hidden in our
behind-the-scenes videos. In this video,
you can see these incomplete equations
on the wall. Using the sub count that
flashed at the beginning to complete the
equation, you'll get these numbers,
which convert to Eterep using ASCII. If
you continue to look through these
videos, you'd find three more locations.
This Super Bowl ticket we gave to a fan
actually switches to say South Pole
instead of Super Bowl on one of our
shorts. Speaking of shorts, this one was
definitely popular. Early on, a lot of
people found this hidden message in the
capital letters of this paragraph. It
spelled out, "This means nothing. I just
wanted to waste your time. LOL."
But see, that's just what I wanted you
to think. Because if you notice, the key
on the cow, walking a cow, the numbers
on the basketball jerseys, the Slack
message from the bear, the pound symbol
on the boxer's hat, and the fact that
all these butlers have doors, you would
reasonably discover that we were
probably just trying to say Quito,
Ecuador, right? Later on, our friends
over at Loan Shark Games would post
three different puzzles to their
socials. Upon solving, you'd get three
different locations.
At this point, the puzzle was only half
complete. And this next group was
massive. It all started at a secret
website called beast.travel, where their
next 40 puzzles were waiting. Beast
Travel featured five sections, each
including a unique set of puzzles, three
of which were already unlocked when you
arrived. There was trips by car, which
had 15 picture puzzles called rebuses,
like this one here with a gate, a scale,
and a scary Grim Reaper. This is how you
decode it. This is a gate, way to Death
Valley, which is the nickname for
Beatty, Nevada.
Next up, trips by horse. This section
was loaded with riddles we called
cryptic trios. Solve the three clues on
a card and you get a random three-word
combo like [music] this one. A push down
sequel to Mist is driven. Thing in this
hunt is a hint. And a little devil
wandering and getting better is
improving. Driven, hint,
>> [music]
>> improving. Sounds like nonsense until
you type it into this geocoding website
like this.
And it's another location pin. We
literally used a global coordinate
system which codes in three-word combos
to hide nine new locations.
Kind of insane. And that third unlock
group was trips by plane, which
contained 16 puzzles known as
geoguessers. A game made possible by
Google Earth and the ability to see all
over the world at any given time. These
16 geoguessers, the nine cryptic
crosswords, and 15 rebuses made up a
total of 40 new puzzles to solve.
[music] Put that together with the 51
locations uncovered in stages 1 through
4 and there's a pretty obvious question.
What do you do with a list of 91 random
locations? Well, you have to solve a
crossword puzzle to [music] find out.
>> Up we go.
>> On Super Bowl Sunday, we released a
giant crossword with zero clues. As the
challenge went on, clues randomly
appeared. Solving this crossword was the
key to unlocking the entire game. It
also came with this weird 11-level array
of empty blocks, which nobody knew what
it meant until I revealed 167 across.
What this puzzle commemorates in 11
words in the theme entries. The answer
was a pun, Super Bowl Sunday. Now
players knew what to look for, soup
themed words. Once extracted, these
words actually fit the array and a new
clue emerged. The phrase Titanic hoop.
You might be asking, what on Earth is a
Titanic hoop? Try a little word
association. Titanic means great and
hoop means circle. Put it together and
you get a great circle, the absolute
largest circle that can be drawn on a
sphere, which on Earth is the equator.
So, the next logical step was connecting
our giant list of 91 locations using
great circles on the actual globe. The
problem was the possibilities were
endless. If you were smart, you made
your way back to beast.travel where
trips by boat was unlocked and waiting.
Inside was a long list of
fill-in-the-blank puzzles, each
including either a car, horse, plane, or
boat. And having collected just as many
locations at this point in the game
as this list is long, players got
started filling in the blanks. When all
the transportation symbols were aligned
like so, there was a new clue just
beneath the surface. It was instructions
for the next puzzle and a good
indication of where to find it. The
final unlocked beast.travel section,
trips by roaming. A poem there hinted of
three points of embarkation. And this
example connecting Haley Bailey, one
cryptic trio, and a bonus crossword
answer did represent three locations:
DeKalb, Illinois; Manistee, Michigan;
and Eyjafjallajökull volcano in Iceland.
That's a mouthful, but it turns out
those three locations did fall perfectly
on a great circle. Here's how it worked.
The 40 locations collected at
beast.travel were connections between
answer pairs from the first stage of the
challenge, like so. Beatty, Nevada
connected Tijuana, Mexico to
Yellowknife, Northwest Territories.
L'Ascension in Quebec connected
Yellowknife, Northwest Territories to
Montreal, Quebec. This final grid was
actually a tool to organize all the
locations players had gathered. And when
complete, they had a properly ordered
list to tie all these locations [music]
together. They noticed something. These
weren't just random lines. This is an R.
Look closely. This [music] is 62. They
were literally spelling out the $1
million vault code. As they worked their
way through the list, plotting point
after point and line after line, a
pattern turned up in the code. R62, L39,
R05.
It didn't take long before players
started submitting this combo as the
final vault code. But, unfortunately for
them, it still wasn't complete.
>> And fortunately for me, I got to keep my
1 million bucks a little bit longer.
>> Two final clues were still left to crack
this challenge once and for all. The
first one had been hiding in plain sight
all along at beast.travel, and the
second one I actually dropped the day
after the Super Bowl on Good Morning
America when Michael Strahan asked me
this.
>> Between you and I, can you give me a
hint?
>> So,
um
Well
>> I guess that's a no, man.
>> No, no, Michael. Let's just flush out
the other clue first. Every map puzzle
at beast.travel was paired with a unique
12-letter word. These were real words
you can literally find in the
dictionary, but until now, they were
pretty meaningless.
>> Here's the trick. When they're stacked
like this, the first letters spell a
secret message. This stack spells
numbers, but that was only part of the
story.
>> Stack the remaining 34 words and you
reveal the final clue. Numbers for this
half would smell as sweet as one.
[music]
If you're wondering what the heck that
means, one guy would have figured it out
instantly, but he's dead.
Sir William Shakespeare, the guy who
wrote Romeo and Juliet and this famous
line, "What's in a name? That which we
call a rose by any other name would
smell as sweet." Yeah, we put
Shakespeare in this challenge. And not
only that back to you, Michael.
>> Between you and I, can you give me a
hint?
>> Maybe look for some numbers in photos
that I took at the Super Bowl or
something, I don't know. And that was
it. If you saw that interview and dug
through my Super Bowl Instagram photos,
you finally had every piece of the
puzzle. Because this specific photo
right here wasn't just the only one with
numbers, it featured Rosé from
Blackpink. And you'd remember numbers
for this half [music] would smell as
sweet as one. And if you'd come this
far, you were one out of 70 million
people who tried to solve this massive
challenge. And you were on the verge of
claiming the $1 prize.
>> On that jet is the person who thinks
they've solved the puzzle.
Is this Colin? Nice to meet you.
>> The vault is right over here. Do you
have the code?
>> I have the code.
>> How many hours have you put into solving
these puzzles?
>> Hundreds and hundreds.
>> Okay. If you input the correct 30-digit
code, that million dollars is yours.
>> Most important number in my life.
>> You have it memorized? You didn't even
write it down?
>> I've got it memorized, man. I see it in
my sleep.
R62
>> Your hands are shaking. Can you hold
your hand out like this? It's a million
dollar combination.
>> 05
>> Oh gosh.
>> L73
The score was 60-0.
>> Yep.
>> Fell on the play number 66.
>> Uh-huh.
>> Order two.
>> 309 on the clock. Ball on the 12.
>> Million dollars.
>> And the rest are some stats I don't
quite understand. 00300
>> Enter.
>> ACCESS GRANTED. BOYS, OPEN IT UP. You're
the first PERSON IN THE ENTIRE WORLD TO
PUT IN THE CODE. WOOHOO!
>> [screaming]
>> THIS IS THE HARDEST THING I'VE EVER
DONE. MY son's going to college.
>> You brought your wife?
>> She is here.
>> Would you say the hobby paid off?
>> It did.
>> [laughter]
>> With around 90 locations and $1 million
on the line, I really didn't think
anyone [music] would solve this puzzle.
But Colin and his team did.
And this puzzle proves that nothing is
ever what it seems, including this
video, because as I mentioned earlier,
there's a puzzle hidden within this
video
created by Colin himself. And the first
person to answer correctly wins $10,000.
So if you think you've solved it, scan
this QR code and enter your final
answer. And as always, thank you for
watching this very special video.
>> Oh
baby,
>> [singing]
>> no.